{
  "version": 2.0,
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "1. The technique agarose gel electrophoresis separated which of the biomolecules?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Lipid",
        "b": "Proteins",
        "c": "Nucleic acids",
        "d": "Carbohydrates"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. Agarose is a polysaccharide extracted from:",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Fungi",
        "b": "Bacteria",
        "c": "Algae",
        "d": "Plants"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. The DNA fragments on an agarose gel can be visualized using:",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Fungi",
        "b": "Bacteria",
        "c": "Algae",
        "d": "Plants"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. The quantification of DNA molecules on a gel can be carried out using:",
      "answers": {
        "a": "pH meter",
        "b": "acetocarmine",
        "c": "ethidium bromide",
        "d": "bromophenol blue"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The DNA fragments are separated through which of the following methods on an agarose gel?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Under the influence of light",
        "b": "Diffusion across gel",
        "c": "Under the influence of electric field",
        "d": "Under the influence of light"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Which of the following options correctly depicts the direction of migration of DNA on an agarose gel?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Positive anode → Negative cathode",
        "b": "Negative anode → Positive cathode",
        "c": "Positive cathode → Negative anode",
        "d": "Negative cathode → Positive anode"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },

    {
      "question": "7. The rate of migration of DNA in agarose gels will not be affected by which of the following factors?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Gel concentration",
        "b": "Voltage",
        "c": "DNA conformation",
        "d": "DNA concentration"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Which fragment of DNA (in base pairs (bp)) would travel the fastest on an agarose gel out of the following:",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Fragment 1- 180 bp",
        "b": "Fragment 2- 600 bp",
        "c": "Fragment 3 – 200bp",
        "d": "Fragment 4 – 120 bp"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Why do the fragments of DNA in gel electrophoresis travel away from the negative electrode?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "DNA is negatively charged so is attracted to the positive end of the unit",
        "b": "DNA is positively charged so is attracted to the negative end of the unit",
        "c": "The agarose gel is negatively charged",
        "d": "The agarose gel is positively charged"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. The fluorescent dye such as Ethidium bromide (EtBr) is used for visualizing DNA. How does EtBr binds to DNA? ",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Stacked between histone molecules",
        "b": "Binds to the nucleotide base",
        "c": "Intercalated between the stacked bases",
        "d": "Binds to the phosphodiester backbone"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    }
  ]
}
